每个人都能看到我的屏幕
And can everybody see my screen
或我共享的白板吗？
or the whiteboard that I shared.
好的，很好。
Okay, good.
大家的锁实验做的怎么样了，
How are people doing with the lock lab,
让我从这里开始，问一下，
let me start there, just ask if,
进展如何，
how progress
或者困难的是什么，或者还好。
and what its more difficult or it's looking okay.
有人想说说自己的感受吗？
Anybody who want to report on their experience so far.
我希望很多人已经开始了。
I hope lots of people have started.
哦，我。
Oh, I.
好的，继续。
Yeah, go ahead.
哦，抱歉，请继续。
Oh, sorry, go ahead.
好的，很好。
Okay, cool.
我来，我来继续说。
I'll go, I'll go.
锁实验，
The lock lab,
我想第一部分， kalloc 没那么糟糕，
I think the first part, the the kalloc was not as bad,
嗯，然后第二部分就有点难了，
well, and then the second part was a bit harder,
嗯，在我看来要难得多。
well, it's a lot harder in my opinion.
你需要想出一个，
You just have to figure out a,
我想最困难的部分是想出一个解决方案，
I guess the hard part was thinking of a solution that,
比如这不会引起死锁，
it's like hey this doesn't cause deadlock,
但是如果你认为有可能会出现死锁，
but then if you think there are cases where like deadlock could happen
如果你获取一个[]，支持获取锁，所有这些，
if you acquire a [] it's lock again and all that stuff,
但是，
but,
是的，我需要考虑，
yeah, I just have to think, you have to think
比如其他情况或所有东西，
like about extra cases and all that stuff
在那之后，情况应该不会那么糟糕。
and after that it shouldn't be that bad.
还有人想分享到目前为止的经验吗？
Anybody else who want to share their experience so far?
我想问一下，
I want to ask,
我们可以在实验里使用比如无锁，
are we allowed to do any part of the lab like lock free,
因为我知道它们的第一部分，
because I know like their first part,
操作指南清晰地表示，
for example it's pretty the instructions said pretty clearly
编写一个并行的内存分配器，
like make a parallel memory allocator,
但是我们能只用无锁，
but can we do it just lock free
并让它保持原样。
and think, you know leave it as it is.
你可以自由地做任何能通过的解决方案，
You're free to do any solution to pass which made great,
无锁也可以，
it's fine lock free,
我会，
I would be,
你当然可以自由去做它。
you are certainly free to do it.
我不会直接从那里开始，
I'd be hesitant to start there,
如果我是你，
if I were you,
我会先从一个更细粒度的锁实现开始，
I would start first with a more fine-grained lock implementation
然后转到无锁实现。
and then move to the lock free implementation.
所以这里不是从无锁开始的的原因是，
So the reason there is not started with a lock free,
如果你使用一个细粒度的，
because if you go to a fine-grain,
你需要做所有并行的东西，
you need to do all of the parallel stuff,
但是如果你直接使用无锁，
but if you just go directly to a lock free one,
你可以将其保留在一个空闲列表中，
then you can keep it on a single free list
你只需要[]，
and you just need to, you just need to [],
释放和分配操作，
the free and allocate operations,
实际上并没有那么糟糕。
which actually isn't that bad.
是的，我想也许，在一个，
Yeah, I think maybe in a,
如果在 kalloc 的情况下只有一个列表，
if there's a single list in the case of the kalloc,
可能是那种情况，
that might be the case,
我想无锁的[]会是一个更复杂的问题。
I think you know the lock free [] is going to be a more complicated.
是的，那是我不敢做的。
Yeah, that I'm scared to do.
但是，这是正确的反应。
But, that's the right reaction to have.
还有其他人吗？
Anybody else?
我发现调试这些问题有点困难，
I found it a bit hard to debug those problems,
因为不能直接地了解发生了什么，
because it's not immediately clear what is happening,
所以我们必须去，
so we have to go
设置 gdb ，中断，中断，中断，是的。
and set with gdb and break break break, and yeah.
是的，我想惟一的，
Yeah, I think the only,
我害怕这些锁实验的一个原因是，
one reason I'm always scared to get these lock labs,
像我说过的，这些实验更难调试，
as I said, labs you know they're harder to debug,
而且 bug 可能不会在每次运行时都出现。
and you know the bug might not show up on every run.
但是，它是非常有教育意义的，
And but hopefully it is very educational,
因为学习程序锁在内核中是一件真实的事，
because learning a program locks inside the kernel is a real thing,
但这绝对是一个核心挑战。
and but it is definitely a core challenge.
这里可能有一件事，
One thing about maybe there's a you know for the,
下一个实验不涉及任何并发，
of course, you know the next lab actually doesn't involve basically any concurrency,
希望这会更直接。
and should hopefully that will be much more straightforward.
好的。
Okay.
我想，你如何，
I gue-, I guess, how do you,
你如何高效地调试并发程序，
how do you efficiently or effectively debug concurrent programs,
比如所有使用 gdb 的多线程那样。
like with all those multiple threads using gdb.
我使用非常基本的东西，
I use very basic stuff,
我使用 print 语句。
I have use print statements.
我主要依靠的是，
But the main thing I rely on is
我尝试写下或断言不变量，
I sort of tried to write down or assertions for invariants,
在我认为应该是 true 的任何点。
that I think should be true at every point.
如果断言失败，
And if the assertion goes off,
然后我知道我的想法有问题，
then I know that you know there's something wrong in my thinking
或者断言是错的。
or assertion was wrong.
然后我想一会儿，
And then I think for a while
试着决定它是什么，
and try to decide what it is,
然后从那里出发。
and then go from there.
正常的，
The normal,
对于许多其他设置，
for many other settings,
有竞争检测器可以帮助你，
there are race detectors that can help you,
并且标志代码可能看起来，
and you know basically flag code that may looks like,
它可能有问题，
it might be having problems
或者受竞争检测器影响，
or as prone to race conditions,
但那是一整套其他的工具，
but that's a whole set of other tools,
我们没有用到的东西。
that we're not using.
它也不是那么好，
And it's not that good,
但这是一大步，
but there's a little bit of a big step
让这些启动并继续运行。
to actually get that all up and going and running.
这是人们使用竞争探测器的另一种机制。
So that's the other mechanism that people use race detectors.
基本上标志，任何更新或写入的共享变量，
Basically flag, any any shared variable that is updated or write
不需要持有一个锁。
without actually holding a lock.
这对解决死锁没有帮助，
That doesn't help with deadlocks,
比如，在这个实验中的 bcache 锁，
for example in this lab in a bcache lock,
你会遇到死锁，
you know you get deadlocks,
死锁往往更容易进行调试，
deadlocks are tend to be easier to do debug, correct,
因为你会遇到 panic ，
because you can get the panic
然后你可以在 gdb 中查看 backtrace ，
and then you can look at the gdb in the backtrace
看看什么引起了死锁。
and see actually was involved in the deadlock.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，另一个建议，
Okay, another suggestion,
有人在反馈中说的，
actually somebody posted on the feedback,
课程更少了，
is you know classes are tend is getting a little bit lower
比起学起刚开始的时候，
than in the beginning of the semester,
我想我们足够小，
and I think we might be small enough,
或者人数合适，
or the size that it may be perfectly fine
打开摄像头。
to actually have cameras on.
所以我想鼓励你，
And so maybe I want to encourage you to
如果你提问，可以打开你的摄像头，
if you ask a question to turn on your camera,
希望能改善我们的体验，
you know will hopefully improve in our experiences,
如果你看到的是教室，
if you've seen the classroom
而不是虚拟会议。
as opposed to in a virtual meeting.
而且你也不用一直看着我。
And you don't have to look at me.
好的，那么，
Okay, so,
好的，今天的课程，
okay, today's lecture,
今天的课程是
so today's lecture is going to be
关于文件系统的崩溃安全，
about crash safety and crash safety of file systems,
这不是一般形式的崩溃安全，
and this is not crash safety in its most general form,
我真正关注的是一个特定的问题，
actually I'm really focusing on a particular problem,
或者一个特殊的问题，
or a specific problem,
也就是，崩溃或断电
namely a crash or power failure
可能会导致磁盘上的文件系统
can lead on-disk file system
处于不一致的状态，或不正确的状态。
to be in an inconsistent state or an incorrect state.
我的意思是，不正确的状态是，
And what I mean, with an incorrect state is
比如一个数据块属于两个文件，
you know for example a data block belongs two files,
或者一个 inode 分配给不同的文件。
or an inode is allocated to different files.
所以这个问题可能出现的情况是，
And so the scenario where this problem might sort of appear is,
假设你运行 make ，
let's say you know you're running make,
make 与文件系统交互，
make pretty file system interact with the file system,
读写文件，
reads writes files
在这个过程中，发生了断电，
and somewhere during you know that thing, a power failure happens,
可能是你的笔记本电脑没电了，
you know maybe your laptop run out of battery,
也许你的房子刚刚断电了，
you know maybe the power just dropped to your house,
你重新启动，
and you know you reboot,
当电源在某一时刻恢复，
the power comes back on at some point,
你重新启动机器，
you reboot the machine, machine comes back up
然后你会再次得到提示符，
and then you get a prompt again,
你运行 ls ，
you run ls
并且希望你的文件系统处于良好状态，
and you hope basically that your file system is in a good state,
在仍然可以使用的状态。
in the state actually can still use it.
所以，我们关注的特定故障或崩溃是
And so the particular failures or crashes that we're concerned about are
文件系统操作期间的电源故障，
basically power failures during file system operations
或者内核死机，
or the kernel panics,
当运行文件系统操作时，
you know while running some file system operation,
xv6 发生死机，
xv6 is panics,
大多数内核发生死机，
most kernels are panics,
可能是某些内核错误导致死机，
you know maybe there're some kernel bug that causes a panic
突然之间你的系统失效。
and you know suddenly your system just fails.
你希望的情况是，
And what you'd like to be the case
在重启之后，你可以做一些事情，
that after rebooting you can actually do something,
或者你仍然可以使用文件系统。
or you can still use the file system.
这可能会想到一些东西，
And this might be something where you're thinking,
这怎么可能不对，
well, how could that not be, right,
因为文件系统存储在持久化存储介质上，
because the file system stored on a persistent storage medium
所以，如果出现电源故障，
and so if the power fails,
介质应该是好的，
you know that medium should be good,
那么一旦机器恢复工作，
then so once machine comes back up,
你写的所有块都应该在那里。
you know all the blocks that you've written should be there.
我们将看到许多棘手的情况，
And we'll see that the tricky cases
很多文件系统操作是多步操作。
that many file system operations have multi-step operations.
真正需要注意的是
And really what is important to note
如果我们在错误的地崩溃，
and if we if we crash just in the wrong place,
在这些多步操作中，
in these multi-step operations,
文件系统可能会不一致，
the file system actually may end up being an this inconsistent
在很短的时间内，
for that short period of time
如果断电正好发生在那里，
and if the power fail just happened there,
可能会有不好的事情发生。
you know something bad could happen.
这就是我们今天关注的问题，
And so that is sort of the problem that we're focusing on today
这与别的问题不同，
and so this is different from the problem
比如，这里出现断电，
that for example whatever you know there's a power failure
并且你的磁盘着火了，
and your disk caught fire
那里什么都没有了，
and so there's nothing there anymore
你需要，
and you need to,
在这种情况下，这是一个完全不同的问题，
in that case, you need you need there's a completely different problem,
有不同的解决方案，
that has different solutions,
比如，你必须取回你的文件系统备份，
you know, for example you have to go back to backup of your file system,
重新安装文件系统，等等。
reinstall your file system, etc etc.
所以这不是我们关心的问题。
So that's the problem we're not worried about.
我们真的关心的是
We're really worried about
多步操作作过程中发生故障的问题。
the specific problem of failure happening right during a multi-step operation.
好的，这个问题的解决方案是，
Okay, and the solution for that specific problem that
我们将要探索的是一种叫做日志的东西，
we're going to be exploring is something that is called logging,
这是一个非常流行的解决方案，
and this is a very popular solution,
最初来自数据库世界，
originally coming out of the database world,
但是现在有很多文件系统使用日志。
but a lot of file systems that use logging these days.
我们会，
We're gonna,
它很受欢迎的一个原因是
it's very one reason it's popular is
因为这是一个非常规范的解决方案，
because it's a very principle solution,
我们将看到 xv6 中日志的实现，
and we're going to see the implementation of logging in xv6
当然， xv6 的实现非常简单，
and of course xv6 has a very simple implementation,
就像日志的最小实现，
like a bare minimal implementation of logging,
只是为了演示关键思想，
just to demonstrate in the key ideas,
即使只是一个基本框架，
and even that sort of a very bare bone,
日志实现仍然有一些问题，
log implementation actually has several issues,
我们将要讨论，
that were going to be talking about
这就是为什么值得去研究它。
and that's why it's worth you know studying it.
我们会看到 xv6 解决方案的一个缺点是，
One downside as we'll see is the xv6 solution is
因为简单，它的性能也不是很好，
because of simplicity, its performance is also not so great,
即使日志系统原则上可以获得良好的性能。
even though logging systems in principle can get a good performance.
所以我们下周要做的是，
And so what we'll do next week is
看看如何实现一个高性能的日志系统，
actually look how, how to implement a high performance logging system
通过学习 Linux ext3 文件系统使用的日志系统，
by studying the logging system the Linux ext3 file system uses,
但那是下周的事了。
but that's next week.
另一个，今天我想说的一个小点是，
Another, may be small a point I want to make today is
这是我们最后一节 xv6 课，
this is our last xv6 lecture
从现在开始，我们将转向论文，
and from now on, we're going to be switching to papers,
因为在某些方面，我们所做的是
because in some ways, what we've done is
我们已经涵盖了基本概念，
we've covered you know the basic concepts
我们可以通过阅读论文了解更高级的操作系统思想。
and we can start looking at more advance operating system ideas by reading papers.
好的？
Okay?
到目前为止，有什么问题吗？
Any questions so far?
好的，很好。
Well, good.
好的，让我回顾一下这些场景，
Okay, so let me go back a little bit about the scenarios
我们在这节课中要关注的。
that were really, that we're focusing about in in this lecture.
所以，文件系统操作，
So file systems, file system operations,
比如创建文件，写入文件，
like creating a file, writing a file,
都是多步的磁盘操作。
are multi-step disk operations.
我们在上周一看到，
And we saw that last week on Monday,
我们讨论了 create 是如何实现的，
we talked about how create is implemented,
比如创建文件或写入文件，
like creating a file, or writing to a file,
我们经常看到事件序列，
we often see that you know the sequence of events,
或者步骤序列是分配 inode ，
or something the sequence of steps are allocated inode,
标记在磁盘上分配 inode ，
mark the inode allocated on disk,
然后写入包含 inode 的目录，
then you know write the directory block that contains that inode
这就是我所说的多步操作。
and so those are the multi-steps that I'm talking about.
如果我们在两个步骤之间崩溃，
If we get a crash between two of the steps,
这个崩溃可能导致，
that crash can leave,
可能会破坏文件系统不变性。
may leave, may leave the file system invariance violated.
破坏不变性，我说的是形式的不变性，
And violent the invariance, I'm talking about are invariance of the form,
每个块要么是空闲的，
you know every block is either free
要么分配给一个文件，而不是两个文件。
or allocated to one file and not to two files.
我们想要确保这件事发生，
And you know we want to make sure that this happens,
即使这些失败发生在这些操作之间。
despite you know these failures right between these operations.
风险是如果不变性被破坏，
Yeah, and the risk is if if the invariance are violated,
重新启动后可能会发生不好的事情，
that bad things can happen after reboot,
你可能马上又会崩溃。
you know the, you might crash again immediately.
因为有一些数据结构，
Because you know there's some data structure,
文件系统处于一种状态，
the file system you know in a state
文件系统无法处理，
that the file system actually can't really deal with,
在这个数据结构上这种状态，
on this data structures in such a state,
文件系统不能再处理它们了，
[] that the file system really can't process them anymore,
或者更有可能你没有崩溃，
or more likely you're not crash, no crash,
但是数据可能会丢失，
but you know data may get lost,
或者你读取或写入不正确的数据。
or you read or write incorrect data.
我们会看几个例子，
And we'll see a couple of examples,
为了更清楚地说明这一点，
you know to make it more clear,
但这些都是我们要担心的风险。
but so these are the risks that we're worried about.
我不知道，有没有人在个人生活或日常生活中，
I don't know if anybody actually every personal life or in your daily life
使用电脑时遇到问题，
using computers actually has experienced a problem
你在文件系统中出现故障，
where basically, you had a failure in the file system
你有一个断电故障，
where you had a failure, had a power failure,
你的机器或你的手机重新启动，
your machine rebooted or your phone restarted
之后就无法使用了。
and basically unusable afterwards.
一个原因可能是不寻常的，
One reason that might be unusual,
因为文件系统没有正确恢复。
because actually the file system just didn't recover correctly.
好的，为了说得更清楚，
Okay, so to make it more clear,
让我们来看一个关于 xv6 的例子，
let's just let's look at an example in the context of xv6,
我想把这个风险说得更具体一点，
I like to make this risk a little bit more concrete,
让我们看看 xv6 中的一个例子，
let's look at an example in the context of xv6
看看会出现什么问题。
and to see what actually go could go wrong.
记得，周一的 xv6 文件系统，
So remember the, for Monday, the xv6 file system,
非常简单的文件系统有一个简单的磁盘布局，
very simple file system has a simple disk layout,
你知道超级块，
you know super block, a super block,
这是日志，我们今天要讨论很多，
there's the log, that we're going to be talking about a lot today,
我们周一没有谈到，
that we didn't talk about on Monday,
inode 是一些块包含，
where inodes you know set of blocks that actually contain,
每个块可能包含多个 inode ，
each and each block may contain multiply inodes,
位图块来记录哪些块是空闲的，哪些不是，
and bitmap block to record which blocks are free and which are not free,
然后数据块包含文件系统的实际数据。
and then the data blocks actually contain the actual data of the file system.
你还记得，周一的课上，
You remember from Monday's lecture,
我分析了这里的输出，
I reproduce the trace here,
我们了解了文件是如何创建的，
you know we looked at actually a how files created
我们看到了单个文件的创建。
and you know we see that the creation of a single file.
好的，稍等一下。
Well, wait a second.
单个文件的创建由多个操作组成，
The, the creation of a single file consists of multiple operations,
比如，在这个特定的场景中，
for example in this particular scenario,
我在幻灯片的这里，
that I've here on the, on on this slide,
我们看到， inode 被分配，
we see the, you know inode is allocated
我们知道这个，因为块 33 正在被写入，
and we know this, because there's block 33 is being written,
我们看到 inode 正在初始化，
do we see that the inode is being initialized,
然后再写入块 33 ，
then write again to block 33,
然后我们看到块 46 被写入，
then we see the block 46 is written
这个写入的原因是，
and that reason is written is,
大概是因为包含 x 的目录块，
presumably because you know the directory block that actually contains x
并且 x 的 inode 编号被写入磁盘。
and the inode number for x is written to the disk.
然后 root inode 被更新，
Then the inode, root inode updated
反映目录的大小增大，
to reflect that the directory has grown in size
包含这个特定文件 x ，
to contain this particular file x
然后 inode 更新了。
and then you know inode updated.
所以我们想了解的是，
So, what we want to understand is
会发生什么，什么会出现问题。
what happens, like what could possibly go wrong, right.
假设我们在这里遇到电源故障，
So let's say you know we have a power failure right here,
这是电源故障或内核崩溃。
so here is power failure or kernel crash.
那么断电后会发生什么，
So what happens after the power failure,
所有内存中状态都会丢失，
correct all the in-memory state is lost,
因为内存中的状态数据在 RAM 中，
because in-memory state data that's actually in RAM,
比如所有进程，所有文件描述符，
like all the processes, all the file descriptors,
所有内存中的缓存都消失了，
all the in-memory caches are gone,
因为内存不是持久的，
because memory is not persistent
我们唯一剩下的东西就是磁盘上的，
and the only thing that we have left is what actually is on the disk,
所以只有数据结构，位和字节，
so only the data structures, the bits and bytes,
它们在磁盘上，在断电后仍然存在，
they're actually sitting on the disk are survived the power failure,
因为那个介质具有耐久性。
because that actually medium is you know persistence or has durability.
所以我们想知道，想理解，
And so we want to know, like want understand,
如果我们在这里崩溃，并且没有额外的机制，
so if we crash here and we have no additional mechanisms,
或者没有我们将要讨论的日志，
or no logging as we're going to be talking about,
没有额外的机制，
we have no additional mechanisms,
会有多糟糕。
how how bad is it.
我们在这里有什么风险？
What risk are we running here?
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
基本上，我们写入块 33
So basically you know we've written block 33
来记录已分配的 inode ，
to record the inode has been allocated,
然后我们断电了，
then we had a power failure
然后我们又恢复了。
and then we come back up.
继续， Brandon 。
Go ahead Brandon.
这是不是说我们丢失了这个块，
This does that mean we lose the, lose this block,
比如它有数据，但其实不是。
it's like it seems like it's populated, but it's actually not.
是的，没错，我想我们丢失了整个块，
Yeah, correctly, I think we're losing, we're losing the whole block,
但是我们使用了 inode x ，
but we used inode x, correct inode x,
并且标记为已分配的 x 的 inode 已经在磁盘上分配，
and inode for x that was allocated or marked as allocated is allocated on disk,
但是我们没有放入任何，
but we have not put in any,
我们没有成功放入任何目录里。
we've not succeeded, correct, put in any directory.
所以在磁盘上，分配了一个 inode ，
So basically on the disk, you know there's an inode allocated,
但它不会出现在任何目录中，
but it doesn't appear in any directory,
所以我们甚至不能删除它。
so we can't even remove it right.
所以，这里发生的是
And so basically what will this cause has to happen is
我们丢失了一个 inode 。
we lose lose an inode.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
你可能会想，也许我应该做的是，
You might think, well maybe what I should do is,
也许我应该重新安排写入顺序。
maybe I should reorder the write.
以某种方法，希望这个，
And, in a way you know then hopefully you know this,
我们不会丢失 inode ，
you know we don't lose the inode,
比如，我们可以试着做的是，
so for example another thing we could try to do is
我们要做的是，
say well what we'll do is,
我们先写入 46 ，
we'll write 46 first,
更新 inode 更新目录，
basically update the inode update directory, right,
目录 inode 写入 32 ，
the directory inode you know write 32
然后在磁盘上标记 inode 已分配，
and then will actually mark the inode is allocated on disk,
标记为已分配。
to mark indicate that mark is allocated.
所以，我们以不同的顺序执行相同的一组操作。
So we do the same set of operations in a slightly different order.
希望我们能够避免这种丢失 inode 的问题。
In the hope that we should avoid this losing of the inode problem.
这能行得通吗？
And would this work?
好的，我们应该问自己，
Well, the thing that we should ask ourselves
比如，让我们考虑一下这个时间点，
like you know let's think about this point in time,
我们假设在这里发生了崩溃，
let's say a crash happens like right here
或者发生电源故障，
or power failure happens
正好发生在更新目录之后，
right between updating the directory basically,
分配磁盘的 inode 之前，
but before we allocated the inode on disk
现在电源故障，
and now you know when power fails,
机器又恢复了，
machine comes back up
我们看看文件系统，
and we look at the file system,
文件系统将处于什么状态。
you know what state will the file system be in.
你会认为它仍然是一个空闲的 inode 。
You'll still think it's a free inode.
是的，会发生什么，
Yeah, what would happen if,
比如我们读取目录中的文件 x ，
for example we read you know file x in the directory,
在根目录中，
in the root directory,
因为它现在这里面，这个数据块。
because it is in there now, correct, this data block.
我们将读取的 inode ，
We're going to be reading the inode,
它甚至没有分配，标记为未分配。
that actually is not even allocated, correct, marked unallocated.
更糟糕的是， inode 可能会再次分配，
And worse, what could happen is, correct, inode it might be allocated again,
或者它可能真的被分配了，
or it might actually really be allocated,
因为未分配的标记是在不同的文件，
because marks unallocated to actually in fact a different file, right,
所以现在我们有两个文件，它们可能，
and so now we have two files that might actually,
两个文件共享，
two files that actually share,
尽管它们完全不同，
even though they're completely different,
但它们共享相同的 inode ，
they share the same inode,
比如，一个文件属于用户一，
for example if one file would be owned by user one
而另一个文件属于用户二，
and one by user two,
那么用户而可以读取用户一的文件数据。
then basically user two could read user one file data right.
所以这也不是好事，对吧。
So that's no good, either, right.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
所以改变顺序，
So basically switching the order
这并不能真正解决我们的问题。
you know it's not really going to solve our problem.
你会遇到我们以前遇到的不同的问题。
You would just basically get a different problem that we had before.
好的，我们再看一个例子。
Okay, let's look at one more example.
这是写入文件 x 的例子。
Here's the example of writing to file x.
所以一旦我们分配了文件，
So once we have the files allocated,
假设所有文件都成功了，
let's say that all succeeded,
现在我们执行 write 系统调用，
and now we're executing the write system call
而 write 系统调用也执行多次写入操作，
and the write system call also does a multiple writes operations
我们在周一看到的，
which we saw on Monday,
比如，它分配块，在这里是块 45 ，
for example it will allocate a block, in this case block 45,
所以它在空闲映射中设置一位，
so it sets a bit in the free map,
块 45 是位图块，
block 45 is the bitmap block,
所以它在位图中分配一个块，
so it allocates a block in the bitmap,
在位图块中分配一个位，
allocates a bit in the bitmap block
表示那个块已经被分配，
to indicate the the block has to be allocated,
那个块，我猜是 595 。
that block turns out to be I guess 595.
然后我们把字符 h 写如 595 ，
And then we write you know the character h you know to 595
然后是字符 i ，
and then the character i,
我们更新 inode 。
you know we update the inode.
好的，现在我们可以问自己同样的问题了，
Right, now we can ask ourselves the same question,
比如如果我们崩溃会发生什么，
like what will happen if we crash,
比如，我们在这里崩溃，
so for example, let's say we allocate crash right here,
在写入位图块之后，
between you know writing the bitmap block,
在写入 inode 之前。
before we allocate before we actually write a inode.
所以，在这里崩溃。
So crash here.
所以重新启动后，我们又回来了，
And so we reboot, we come back up
这是一种特殊的状态，
and this is in a particular state
风险是什么？
and you know what, what is the risk?
我们使用了数据块，但我们失去了它。
We use it data block, but we lose it.
是的，我们又失去了，
Yeah, we lose it again, right,
因为块被分配了，
because the block is allocated,
但没有出现在任何文件中，
but doesn't show up in any file,
因为它没有写入任何 inode ，
because it hasn't been written into any inode,
所以我们丢失了一个数据块。
so we lose a data block.
你可能会想，
You might think,
好吧，也许是因为我们写入顺序错了，
okay, well maybe you know just because we wrote them in the wrong order,
我们应该做的是，
what we should have done is
我们首先应该做的是写入 inode ，
what we should have done is at first write in the inode,
所以先写入 33 ，使用 595 ，
so first write 33 with the, you know with 595
它是间接块或直接块。
as in the either is an indirect block or direct block.
然后我们标记 inode 块为已分配，
And then you know actually we will mark the inode, the block is allocated,
然后我们写入 45 。
so then we'll write you know 45.
如果我们修改顺序，
If we change the order,
因为我们要避免丢失数据块，
because we want to avoid these lost data block,
我们这样修改顺序。
we change order in this way.
现在我们考虑这种情况，
And now let's consider the case,
如果这里出现故障。
if there's a failure right here.
风险是什么？
What is the risk?
文件的大小与实际分配的数据块不匹配。
The size of the file is not compatible with actually how many data blocks are allocated.
也许是这样，
That might be,
虽然我认为写入 33
although I think it's the write of 33
实际上更新了大小和块编号。
actually update both the size and you know the the block number.
噢。
Oh.
所以这可能是正常的。
So that might be might work out okay.
如果有两个单独的写入，那将是一个问题，
If there were two separate writes, that would be a problem,
但这里有个更大的问题。
but there's some bigger problem here.
是不是那个，
Is that the,
所以这个文件里面有，
so the file has the,
所以它有数据块，
so things that it has the data block,
但是数据块被标记为未分配，
but the data block is marked as unallocated
其他文件也可以使用它。
and other files can also use it.
是的，这才是真正的大问题，
Yeah, that's the real big problem here is that,
inode 块 595 属于那个文件，
you know the the inode things 595, block 595 belonged belonged to that file,
但是在磁盘上，它仍标记为未分配，
but actually on disk it's still marked as unallocated
所以，当稍后创建另一个文件时，
and so when later another file was created,
那个块可能会用于另一个文件。
you know that block actually might be used for that other file.
所以现在有一个文件拥有 595 ，
And so now certainly one file things, it owns 595,
但其他文件也是这样的，
but actually other file does,
实际上这两个文件都有 595 ，
in fact both files will have 595
在它们的 inode 的块编号中，
in their block numbers for their inode
如果一个用户拥有该文件，
and basically you know if one user owns that file,
另一个用户拥有另一个文件，
the other user in the other file,
他们可以读写对方的数据，
that can actually read write to each other's data, right,
这显然不是我们想要的。
that's clearly not what we want.
文件系统应该保证，
You know the file system should guarantee
每个块只属于一个文件，
that every block only belongs in one file
不属于其他文件或是空闲的。
and no other file or is free.
好的？
Okay?
所以这可能会导致安全问题，
So this could lead to security problems,
块在多个文件之间共享，
basically block is shared among multiple files,
这绝对是错的。
and that's definitely wrong.
关于可能出现的问题，这些能理解吗？
Does it make sense, in terms of the problems that can appear?
再说一次，这里真正的问题是，
And again, you know the real issue here is,
不是看写入的顺序，
not to watch the ordering of the writes,
但这里真正的根本问题是，
but the real underlying problem here is
我们在进行多次写入，
that we're just doing multiple writes
它必须以原子操作的形式出现在磁盘上。
and it basically have to show up on disk as an atomic operation.
好的，所以我们在这节课中要研究的解决方案是日志。
Okay, so the solution that we're gonna explore in this lecture is logging.
正如我之前所说的，
And as I said before,
这是文件系统中常用的解决方案，
this is a common solution used in file systems
来源于数据库资料。
and originating actually out of the database literature.
它有几个很好的特性，
And it actually has a couple good properties,
其一，它使系统调用或文件系统调用是原子的，
one, it's going to make basically system calls or file system calls atomic,
我的意思是，
with that, I mean,
如果创建文件，
so if a create file
或者调用 create 或 write ，
or you can call create you call write,
所有系统调用的作用，
basically all the effects of that system call
一起出现或完全不出现，
use all appeared altogether or none of them,
所以，这避免了这个问题，
so that avoids this problem
只有部分写入出现在磁盘上的问题。
of only some subset of the writes actually showing up on disk.
它拥有的第二个好的属性，
Second good property it has,
它允许快速恢复。
it allows for fast recovery.
所以在重启之后，
So after reboot,
我们不需要做很多工作来修复文件系统，
turns out we don't actually have to do a lot of work to repair the file system,
实际上只需要很少的工作。
actually a very minimal amount of work.
这与其他一些解决方案形成了鲜明对比，
And this is in contrast to some other solution
我没有说的方案，
and I'm not talking about,
你去检查文件系统，
which is basically you go and inspect the file system,
可能你读取文件系统的所有块，
maybe you read all the blocks of the file system
或者读取所有 inode 块，
or read all the inode blocks,
读取所有位图块，
read all the bitmap blocks
所以检查，
and so check out
文件系统是否仍处于正确的状态，
whether the file system is still in the correct shape
或许还可以进行修复。
and maybe repair things.
日志有这个很好的属性，恢复很快。
Logging has this nice property that actually the recovery is fast.
最后，在原则上，它可以是非常高的性能，
And finally, it is in principle, it can be actually very high performance,
虽然要看的这个，
although the one, you know what we're going to be looking
在 xv6 中看到的不是高性能的，
in the context of xv6 is not high performance,
所以我们下周要看这个，
so we're going to look at that next week,
我们将了解如何构建一个日志系统，
we'll see actually how to build a logging system
具有原子文件系统调用，更快的恢复和高性能，
that has atomic file system calls faster recovery and high performance,
今天我们只关注前两个。
today we're going to be just focusing on the first two.
好的。
Okay.
日志的基本思想非常简单，
The basic idea of logging is actually straightforward,
所以你要做的就是把它分成两部分，
and so basically what you do is you divide this into two pieces,
一个是日志，一个是文件系统，
one is the log, one is the file system,
文件系统可能比日志大得多。
and file system might be much bigger than log.
当你需要更新文件系统时，
And when you need to update the file system,
比如更新块 33 或者更新位图块，
so update, let's say block 33 or update the bitmap block,
我们实际上不会更新文件系统块，
we're actually not going to update the file system blocks,
所以我们不会直接更新位图块，
so we're not going to update bitmap block directly,
相反，我们要在右边做的唯一一件事是，
instead the only thing we're gonna do on the right is,
这是我们的内存，
so here's our memory,
我们的内存中有一个块，
we have a block in memory,
比如位图块，它是 45 ，
is say the bitmap block, it's 45
不是把它写入 45 ，
and instead of writing it to 45,
像平常我们做的那样，
where we normally would have done,
我们实际上要做的是写入日志，
what we're gonna do is actually going to write into the log,
我们把它放在这里，
we're going to stick it here
记住它应该是 45 ，
and remember that definitely should go to 45,
我们把它放在那里。
we will put it there.
我们对所有其他的写入也是这样做的，
And we do that with all the other writes too,
比如，我们将 inode 块放在这里，
so for example we'll put inode block there,
如果我没记错的话，应该是 33 ，
you know like maybe 33 I think, if I remember correctly
我们会把它放在这里，
and we'll stick it in there
记住这应该是 33 。
and you know, remember that actually has to go to 33.
所以我们要做的任何写入第一就是日志。
So basically what we do any write his first log.
我们不会直接写入块的所在地，
And so we don't write directly to the home location of the block,
我们只是把它放在日志里。
but we just put it always a log.
然后，在文件系统操作完成时，
Then, at some point when the file system operation is done,
比如，
for example as you know,
我们在前面的幻灯片中看到的四五个写入在日志中，
these four five writes that we saw in the previous slides are in the log,
我们就提交这些操作。
we commit the operation.
它的意思是在日志里的某个地方，
Basically what it means is somewhere in the log,
我们在一个固定的位置标记一个记录，
we just record a record, you know in a fixed location,
这表示，
that basically says,
好的，日志里有 5 个日志，
okay, well you know there are like five logs in the log,
这就是一组写入的日志。
and that is you know the log, set of log the writes.
然后，当我们将所有写入放在磁盘上时，
And then you know when we have all the writes stably on disk,
我们要安装它们，被称为安装阶段。
we're going to actually install them, was called the installation phase.
它的意思是，
And really what that means is,
我们要把这些日志从日志移动到它们的原位置，
we're gonna move you know these logs from the log to their home location,
我们知道这个到 45 ，
so we know this one has to go to 45,
所以我们把它放到 45 ，
so we put it at 45,
这个必须是 33 ，
this one has to go to 33,
我们把它放到 33 ，以此类推。
we put it to 33, etc etc.
一旦我们完成了，
And once we're done,
我们就可以清理日志了，
you know basically we can clean the log
清理日志，
and cleaning the log,
就是重写，把这个 5 设置为 0 。
basically you're rewriting, you know basically setting this five to zero.
这是基本的计划。
And that is a basic plan.
为什么这个计划是好的，
And why is this plan good,
好的，让我们想一想。
well, let's think about it.
假设我们在这里之前崩溃，会发生什么。
Let's say we crash before here, what would happen.
所以让我暂且不提这个问题，
So let me hold that question,
让我在提问之前讨论一件事。
let me actually talk about one thing before asking the question.
假设我们崩溃了，并且重新启动，
Let's say we crash and so we reboot,
在重新启动时，文件系统做了什么，
and on the reboot, there's basically what the file system does,
它查看提交记录，
it looks at the commit record,
查看提交记录的值，
sees what the value of the commit record is,
如果是 0 ，什么都不做，在我们的简单方案中。
if it is zero, you know do nothing in our simple scheme.
如果它大于 0 ，
And if it's bigger to 0,
我们知道日志中有一些块，
we know that there are basically blocks in the log
需要被安装。
that need to be actually installed.
显然我们还没有完成安装，
And we apparently didn't finish the installation,
我们在提交之后崩溃了，
we crashed you know after the commit,
但是在清理日志之前，
but before cleaning the log,
所以我们重新安装，
so basically we re-install,
重新安装之后，我们清理日志。
and after we re-install, we clean the log.
好的?
Okay?
而且这个方案是好的，
And this scheme is good,
因为它确保了无论崩溃发生在哪里，
because it actually ensures that no matter where the crash happens,
我们要么安装了所有的写入块，
we're either install all the blocks of the writes
要么一个都没有安装，
or we install none of them,
但是我们从来不会进入，
but we were never into,
我们永远不会处于一种情况，
we will never end up in a situation
我们安装了一些，而不是所有的写入。
where we installed some of the writes, but not all of them.
为了弄清为什么这是真的，
Just to see why this is true,
让我们来考虑几个可能崩溃的情况。
let's consider a couple cases where things could crash.
所以在一到二之间崩溃，会发生什么，
So things could crash and between one and two, what will happen,
我们会到达什么情况。
in what situation do we end up.
在恢复过程中，我们什么都不做，
Situation in which on recovery, we do nothing
这是可以的，因为没有任何内容写入文件系统。
and that's okay, because nothing has been written to the file system.
是的，就是这样，
Yeah exactly,
所以这就是我们什么都不做的情况，
so this is the case where basically we we just do nothing,
就像这个系统调用没有执行一样，
you know as if the system call basically never executed,
因为如果故障发生得稍早一点，
because if the failure happened slightly earlier,
在文件系统调用开始之前。
right, before the file system calls started.
所以这完全没问题，这是可以接受的。
And so that's perfectly okay, that's acceptable.
好的，如果我们在提交之后安装之前崩溃会怎么样？
Okay, what happens, if we crash, okay, between after committing before being installed?
然后，你只需要重做所有安装，
Then you'll just redo all the installs,
这样就可以恢复到正确的状态。
so you'll kind of restore the correct state.
是啊，确实如此，
Yeah, so exactly,
在这一点上，
so at that point correct,
我们知道所有数据块都在日志中，
we have, we know there are all the blocks are in the log
它们都会被写下来，因为我们提交了，
and they'll be all written, because we committed,
所以，它是整个文件系统操作完成的情况。
so it must be the case that the whole file system operation finished.
所以我们可以把它们放到它们应该在的位置。
So we can basically put them in their location where they should be.
然后我们都处于好的状态，
And then we're all in good shape
所以在这种情况下，所有文件，
and so in this case now all the file,
在这种情况下，就像，
in this case will end up as if the,
就像文件系统调用在崩溃之前完成，
it is if the file system call actually completely just before the crash,
没有什么区别。
there's no difference.
好的？
Okay?
那么，如果在安装过程中崩溃会发生什么，
So what happens if we crash during install
或在清理之前安装过程中，
or like install during install before cleaning,
在这里崩溃。
crash here.
在这种情况下，
In this case,
in this case
我要做第三种情况，
and I will do the third case,
我们安装，在安装过程中，或者在安装之前，
we'll install, during installation, or just before install,
在安装之后清理之前。
after installing before cleaning.
然后会发生什么？
What, what what, what happened then?
在。
On the.
哦，抱歉，在下次重启时，
Oh, sorry, on the next restart,
什么都没有改变，
nothing has really changed,
除了恢复进程，
in terms of the recovery process
我们只是重做日志。
and so we're just going to redo the log.
我们要重做一次日志，
We're going to redo the log again
我们要把内容再复制一遍到各个位置，
and we're gonna copy basically the content again you know to the locations right maybe,
我们可能要做多次，
in fact we might do it multiple times,
这可以吗？
is that okay?
是的，因为这些都是写入，
Yes, because those are just writes,
它们在我们没有改变的特定位置，
and it's, they are to a specific location that we don't change,
就像写入日志里的那样，
like it's written in the log,
所以我们知道每次应该写在哪里。
so we know where we should write every time.
是的，每次我们写的都一样的，
Yeah basically every time we do the same write, correct,
假设在块 45 中，它的值是 10 ，
so let's say in block 45, you know there's the value 10,
我们每次都在 45 位置写入 10
and we're going to write 10 at location 45 every time
这正是它应该的，
and that's exactly what it should be
而且多次重复写也不会有什么坏处。
and repeating that write multiple times doesn't really do any harm, right.
因为我们写的是相同的值，
Because we're writing the same value,
它就应该在那里。
that actually should be there anyway.
所以这很好，
And so it's perfectly fine,
我们可以多次重新安装。
for us to do re-installation multiple times.
当然，在这个时间点，我们不应该执行任何其他文件系统调用，
Of course, we shouldn't serve any other file system calls at this particular point of time,
我们应该在重新启动文件系统之前执行此操作，
we should do this before we restart the file system,
但是，在恢复期间重新启动时，
but while you know what during reboot during recovery,
我们可以这样做。
you know we can just do this, right.
也就是说，安装是幂等的，
Another way of saying, that is that installation is basically idempotent,
你可以多次执行它，
you can just execute it many many times
并产生相同的效果。
and will have the same effect yet.
关于这个的问题？
Question about that?
因为接口只是读和写，
Because the interface is just read and write,
如果我们有追加，这就不安全了，对吧？
if we had an append, this would not be safe, right?
是的，这个[]，
Yeah yeah, this [],
你也可以使追加变得安全，
you can make append safe too,
一种更复杂的日志方案，
a more fancy logging schemes,
但是对于这个的日志方案，
but for this particular logging scheme,
我们不必担心这个。
we don't have to worry about that.
在某种意义上，追加是文件系统级操作，
In fact, in some sense, the append is file system level operation
在这个层面上，我们可以将其作为主题，
and at that level we can make it a topic
使用我们在这里的日志方案。
using the logging scheme, that we're, what we have here.
我明白了，谢谢。
I see, thank you.
我也有一个问题，
I also have a question,
如果在提交时文件系统崩溃，会发生什么情况，
what would happen if the file system crashed while you are committing,
你希望执行多个写入，
so you want to execute multiple writes
然后你只提交其中的一半。
and then you only commit like half of them.
好的，你能说大声点吗，
Yeah okay, so can you speak up a little bit more,
因为你的声音太小了。
because your volume is low.
哦，是的，抱歉，
Oh, yeah sorry,
如果你想一次提交多个写入，
so if you wanted to like commit multiple writes at once,
比如以原子方式，
like in an atomic way,
但是你的系统在提交的过程中崩溃了，
but your system crashes in the middle of committing,
所以你只能提交一半的写入，
so you are only able to commit like half of the writes,
在那种情况下会发生什么？
what would happen in that instance?
好的，有一点很重要，
Okay, so there's a very important point,
我很高兴你问了这个问题。
I'm glad you ask the question.
所以首先，
So first of all,
你提交，提交操作在这里，
the the you commit, in writing this commit operation here, correct,
这是第二步，
this you know step two,
你提交这些操作，
you only execute that commit operation
只在你已经记录了所有写入后，
after you've already logged all the writes,
你打算执行，对吧。
that you were planning to execute, right.
所以，在你提交时，
So at the point you do to commit,
所有写入都在日志中。
all the writes are in the log.
因此，提交操作本身
And so, the commit operation itself
是一个有趣的问题，在那里发生了什么。
is an interesting question, what happens there.
所以，我在幻灯片上标出，
So, the way the way I indicated this on slide,
提交操作写入一个块，
like commit operation writes a single block,
磁盘中的一个扇区。
like a single sector on the disk.
文件系统的标准假设是
And the standard assumption that file systems make is that
单个块写入或单个扇区写入是*原子*操作。
a single block write or single sector write is an atomic operation.
这意味着如果你写入它，
Meaning that if you write it,
将写入整个扇区，或者任何扇区都不写入。
the whole sector will be written, or none of the sector will be written.
所以，扇区永远不会被部分写入。
So the sector will never be written partially.
所以在特定扇区总是有效数据，
And so there's always you know clearly you know valid data in that particular sector
所以这个提交操作写入日志头，
and so basically this operation that commit operation writing the log header,
写入提交记录是真正的提交操作，
is writing the commit record is the real commit operation,
如果成功，并且提交头中是 5 ，
if that succeeds, and there's basically say of five in the commit header,
我们知道日志中有 5 个块，
you know we know that there are five blocks in the log
我们必须重新安装这 5 个块。
and we have to reinstall those five blocks.
如果提交头没有到达磁盘，
If the commit header didn't make it to disk,
则该值仍为 0 ，
then the value will still be 0
我们就当那个事务从未发生过。
and we'll just treat it as if that transaction never happened.
谢谢。
Thank you.
你提到的关键规则，
And the key rule that you're sort of hinting at,
那必须是真的，
that has to be true,
是所谓的预写规则，
is something what's called the write-ahead rule,
意味着日志系统不能安装写入，
which means that a logging system cannot install writes,
直到所有写入到日志中。
until all the writes into, are into log.
关于这个基本方案，有什么问题吗？
Any more questions about this sort of basic plan?
好的？
Okay?
让我们看看。
Let's see.
所以我想，
So what I want to,
有很多不同版本的日志方案，
there are many many different versions of logging schemes
我在这里画了一个非常简单的图，
and I sketched out here a very simple one,
这完全没问题。
you know it's perfectly fine.
有些方案是推迟清理日志，
You know there schemes where basically the cleaning of the log is postponed,
安装被推迟，
installation is postponed until later,
但我将运行这个非常简单的方案，
but I'm going to run sort of this very simple scheme,
下周我们将看到更复杂的日志协议。
and then next week we'll see more sophisticated logging protocols.
但是所有那些记录协议，都遵循这个预写规则，
But all those logging protocols, follow this write-ahead rule,
在你准备提交记录之前，
that before you're ready to commit record,
你必须确保所有写入都在日志中。
you have to make sure that all the writes are in the log.
但是这里面有很多东西，
But then there's a lot of within that,
尽管如此，仍有很大的灵活性，
still there's a ton of flexibility
在设计特定日志协议方面。
in designing a particular logging protocols typically called.
好的，我来看一下，
Okay, I'm gonna look a little bit,
这是如何在 xv6 中表现出来的，
how this then is manifest itself in xv6,
作为一个案例研究，让事情变得更具体。
you know as a case study and to make things really concrete.
好的，在 xv6 中，
Okay, so in xv6, there's sort of,
你会看到两种类型的[]，
you're going to look at two sort of piece of [] you will,
在磁盘上的东西，
the stuff that is actually on disk,
和在内存中的东西，
and that's you know things that are in memory,
在内存中的内容会丢失，
in-memory contents will disappear,
在此过程中，我们应该考虑的是，
on the way we should think about it is that
内存中的内容会在崩溃或断电时消失。
in-memory content will disappear on a crash or power failure.
xv6 日志的结构一直都非常简单，
And the structure of the xv6 log as always pretty simple,
我们在开头有一个块， header 块，
there's actually, we have one block in the beginning, the header block,
这就是我们的提交记录，
and that's basically our commit record,
它包含数字 n ，
you know it contains the number n,
就是日志中的块数，
which is like the number of blocks in the log
然后对于每个块，
and then for each block,
块编号，那个块的所在位置，等等，
the block number, the home location of that block, blah blah blah,
将会是其中的任何一个。
are going to be any of those.
所以，在日志本身中
And so, then in the log itself
是属于它的数据，
are basically is the data, that it belongs to that,
所以，这是 bn0 的数据，
so here is the data of bn0,
这是 bn1 的数据，等等，
here's the data of bn1, etc,
到 bn-1 ，
to bn-1,
这就是日志里的内容。
so that's what's in the log.
所以在日志中只有一个东西，
And there's the only thing, that's sort of in the log,
没有更多的了。
there's nothing more to it.
然后在内存中，当文件系统运行时，
Then in memory where, while the file systems running,
有一个 header 的拷贝版本在内存中，
there's an in copy version in-memory version of the header,
它有 n ，
and it basically has n
它有块编号数组，等等。
and it has array of block numbers, etc.
然后这些块编号
And then you know these block numbers
指向的是位于数据中的块，
refer to block that are sitting in the data,
与块编号相对应，
that actually corresponds to the block numbers
位于内存中数据结构中，
that are sort of sitting in this in-memory data structure,
它们在块缓存中，
they live in the block cache,
现在你已经很熟悉了。
which you know, but now you're well familiar with.
所以，也许这是块 10 ，
And so, maybe this is like block 10,
是日志中的第一个块，
is the first block in the log,
或者让我举一个更具体的例子，
or maybe let me take a more concrete example,
从我们之前的东西来看，
from that lines up with our previous things,
也许这是 45 ，
maybe this is like 45,
在缓存中的某个地方，
and basically you know somewhere in the in cache,
块缓存，
the block cache,
这里是块 45 ，
there's of course whatever block 45,
这是数据。
here is data.
好的？
Okay?
这是一种结构，
That's sort of the structures,
内存中的文件系统所具有的，
that the on-disk in-memory file system has
和在磁盘上的文件系统所具有的，
and on-disk file system has,
在磁盘上的文件系统只有日志，
on-disk file system just has the log,
在内存中含有数据结构
the in-memory has these data structures
用来协调这些将要执行的多次写入操作。
to orchestrate these multi write operations that were going to be doing.
好的？
Okay?
所以，为了更具体一点，
So, to make this a little more concrete,
让我们来看一些代码。
let's look at some code.
这将帮助我们了解一切是如何运行的。
Then that will help us understand how everything works.
所以让我调出一些代码。
So let me pull up some code.
好的，让我把这个放在它旁边，
Okay, let me put this next to it,
我们保留着那张图片，
we keep that picture,
这样我们想看就可以看看，
so that we can look at if we want to
或者我可以指向它。
or I can point to it.
每个人都能看到我的代码吗？
Can everybody see my code?
要有人确认他们看到了 emacs 窗口。
Somebody have to confirmed they seen emacs window.
是的，我们可以看到它。
Yeah we can see it.
好的。
Good.
它够大吗？
Is it big enough?
我觉得挺好的。
I think it's good.
好的。
Okay.
看起来不错。
That looks good.
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，让我们开始，
Okay, so let's start with,
我谈到了事务，
you know I I talked about transactions,
我们不应该提交，直到，
where you you know the fact that you know we should not commit until,
我们不应该提交一次写入，直到所有的写入都完成了。
we should not write to commit a [], until all the writes have done.
所以，这意味着，
And so this means that you should
文件系统操作必须指明
file system operations must indicates
事务的开始是什么，
what the beginning of transaction is
以及事务的结束是什么。
and particularly at the end of the transaction is.
在 xv6 中发生的方式是，
And the way that happens in xv6,
每个文件系统调用，
that every file system call,
这里的 open 对应于 create ，
here's open corresponds to create,
以 begin_op 开始，
basically starts with begin_op
begin_op 表示，开始一个事务，
and begin_op indicates like, okay I want to start a transaction
我希望所有的块写入，
and I want all the block writes
我在 begin_op 和 end_op 之间说做的，
that I've been doing between begin_op and end_op
end_op 是事务的结束，
which is basically the end of the transaction
这些之间的写入操作都是原子的，
to be atomic,
意味着它们全都应用或全不应用。
meaning they should be all applied to, or none of them should applied.
好的？
Okay?
所以，每个 xv6 中的文件系统调用都有这样的结构，
So every file system call in xv6 has that structure,
有 begin_op ，
basically has begin_op,
然后是实现文件系统调用的代码，
then the code and implements the file system call
然后是 end_op 。
and then end_op.
而 end_op 就是提交操作发生的地方。
And that end_op is basically where the commit operation happens.
所以，在 begin_op 和 end_op 之间，
So basically between begin_op and end_op,
磁盘上或内存中数据结构应该更新，
on-disk or in-memory data structure should be updated,
无论内存中日志更新，
whenever the in-memory log may be updated,
或者块缓存可能更新，
the block cache might be updated,
但是在 end_op 之前什么都不会发生，
but nothing really happens until end_op
然后在 end_op 时，
and then end_op time,
我们把东西放到日志中，
we're basically going to put things into the log
然后我们完成了把所有的东西放到日志中，
and then we are done with putting everything in the log,
将写入提交记录或日志头。
will actually you know write to commit record or log header.
好的？
Okay?
那我们开始吧。
So let's.
所以有趣的是，
So what is interesting,
当然，每一次写入，
of course what happens is every write, correctly,
当文件系统调用执行一次磁盘写入时，
whenever one of these file system calls does a disk write,
一些事情一定会发生，
you know something must happen,
所以如果我们回到 fs.c ，
so if we go back for example to fs.c,
查看 ialloc ，
you know look at ialloc,
ialloc 调用，
ialloc basically what it calls,
它没有直接调用 bwrite ，
it doesn't call bwrite directly,
而是调用了 log_write 。
but it actually calls a log_write.
我们将了解 log_write 的作用，
And so we're going to see what log_write does,
log_write 是日志系统实现的功能，
log_write is basically a function implemented by logging system,
每个写入，
and every write
在 begin_op 和 end_op 之间的文件系统调用，
basically a file system call dose between begin_op and end_op,
总是通过 log_write 。
always goes through log_write.
所以这里是 log_write ，
So here's log_write
log_write 实际上相当简单。
and log_write actually reasonable straightforward.
是的，我们写入块，在块缓存中，
Yeah, you know we've written the block, in the block cache,
某个地方 45 ，也许是写入到 45 ，
so somewhere basically 45, maybe this is like the write to 45,
我们已经更新了块缓存中的 45 ，
we've updated you know 45 in the block cache,
现在我们记录在内存中的数据结构中，
now we basically record in the in-memory data structures,
稍后，在提交的时候，
that at some point later, at commit point,
我们能够将日志写入日志。
we were able to write this log into log.
所以，你知道代码是，
And so you know basically you know the code is,
糟糕，
oops,
代码相当简单，
the code is reasonably straightforward,
它获取日志头的锁，
it acquired a lock on the header
并更新日志头，
and basically updates the header,
它说做的是更新 n ，
in particular, what does goes through you know the updates n,
所做的第一件事是，
and when actually the first thing it does,
如果已经有一份 45 的拷贝，
it actually sees if there's already a copy of 45 in the,
如果 45 已经被记录为必须写入，
if 45 is already recorded as being having to write to written to,
如果是这样情况，
and if that's the case,
什么都不用做，因为会写入到 45 。
nothing has to be done, because 45 will be written to.
这样我们就完成了，
And so we're done,
有时称为日志[吸收]。
sometimes called log absorption.
如果快 45 不在数组中，
If you know block 45 is not in the array yet
或者不在块列表或块数组中，
or not in the the list of blocks or the array of blocks,
需要写入磁盘，
that needs to be written to disk,
那么这段代码所做的事就是，
then basically you know the only thing, this particular piece of code does is
增加并将需要写入的块编号放入
basically bump up and stick that block number that needs to be written
下一个条目或这个条目。
into the next entry or into that entry.
然后它做的另一件事，
Then the only other thing it does
我稍后会谈到，
and I'll talk about this later,
它将把块放入缓冲区缓存中，
it will pin the block in the buffer cache
让我把原因推迟一会，
and let me postpone why a little while,
我稍后会再谈这个问题。
but I will come back to that later,
这就是 log_write 所做的全部工作，
and that's actually all that log_write there doing.
所以，每个需要更新块的文件系统调用，
So every file system call that needs to update a block,
更新块缓存中的块，
updates the block in the block cache
它会将它附加到内存中的数据结构中，
and it basically it appends it to this in-memory data structure,
除非它已经在那里了，
unless you know it's already there,
在这种情况下，只需要吸收它。
in which case you know just absorbs it.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
那么是否意味着 bwrite 根本不应该单独使用？
So does it mean that bwrite shouldn't be used by itself at all?
抱歉，请再说一遍。
Sorry, say again.
bwrite 不应该单独使用，只能用作。
bwrite shouldn't be used by itself, only as.
是的，没错，
Yes that's correct,
一种考虑的方式是，
basically all you, one way to think about is
在文件系统中的每个 bwrite 都被 log_write 替换。
that every bwrite in the file system is replaced by log_write.
好的，现在我们看看 end_op 发生了什么，
Okay, so now let's see what actually happens at end_op,
因为那是令人兴奋的部分。
because that's where the exciting part happens.
有几个案例我暂时不谈，
And there's a couple of cases that I just wanna avoid talking about,
稍等一会，
a little bit later,
因为即使是这个简单的日志系统也有一些微妙的复杂性，
because they even this simple logging system actually has some subtle complexities
这些代码的大多数开头涉及到这些微妙的复杂性。
and most of the [beginning] of this code deals with these subtle complexities.
但是如果你想得到一个正常的情况，
But if you want to get a normal case,
有一个简单的情况，
you know there's or there's the simple case
没有其他文件系统操作正在进行，
where no other file system operations are in progress,
我们正在执行创建文件，
we are executing create file
我们已经快到可以提交的地方。
and basically we're getting to the point where we want to commit.
因此代码非常简单并调用 commit ，
And so the code is pretty straightforward and calls commit,
所以让我们来看一下 commit 。
so let's look at the commit.
这里是 commit ，
So here's commit,
[] commit 执行写入日志的步骤，
[] commit does to basically steps basically writes the log,
写入所有这些块编号，
that's basically writing all these, all these block numbers,
它们位于内存 header 中，
that are sitting you know in the in-memory header,
将它们全部写入磁盘上的 header ，
writes them basically all to the header on disk,
包括数字 n 。
including you know there's number n.
好的，让我们看看，
Right, and so let's see,
这是 write_head 所做的，抱歉，
that is that's what write_head does, sorry,
write_log 写入块
write_log basically writes you know the blocks
从缓冲区缓存到它们各自的日志中。
from the buffer cache into their respective into the log itself.
让我们看看上面的 write_log ，
So let's see write_log, right above here,
看它是怎么做的，
you see what it does,
它检查这个数组，一次一个，
it goes through you know this array one at a time
并且写到日志中的日志位置。
and basically writes that to the log position in the log.
好的，读日志块，然后把它放进去，
Okay, so read you know the log block, then sticks it in there,
复制它，然后把它写入磁盘。
by copying it, and then writing it actually out to the disk.
所以这保证日志 45 在这里，
So this basically ensures that log 45 laid up here,
比如说这是 32 ，
you know say this is 32,
它将在那里，等等。
that will end up there etc etc.
然后，最后，
Then, at the end,
到目前为止我们还没有提交，
so at this point we have not committed yet, correct,
我们所做的唯一一件事是
the only thing we've done is
把数据块放入日志，
basically putting blocks into the log,
如果我们在这个时间点崩溃，
and if we were crash at this particular point in time,
在调用 write_head 之前，在 write_head 成功前，
before calling write_head before write_head succeeded,
就像事务根本没有执行一样。
and basically as if the transaction didn't execute at all.
所以让我们来看一下 write_head ，
So let's look at the write_head,
write_head 是我前面所说的提交点，
so that write_head is what I called earlier, basically the commit point,
提交点很直接，
and the commit point, basically you know basically it's straightforward
到达磁盘上块的头，
and reach the head of block from disk,
可能位于缓冲器缓存中，
which is probably sitting in the buffer cache,
把拷贝放在最后，
it you know puts the copies the end,
那个块的后面，
you know this end into that block,
把所有块编号放到那个数组，放到那个块，
puts all the block numbers into that array into that block
它写入那个特定的块。
and it basically writes that that particular block.
这个，
This is the,
这个 bwrite 是什么，是那个提交点吗？
this bwrite what is that, is that the commit point?
如果在 bwrite 之前发生崩溃，会发生什么呢？
If a crash happens before this bwrite, what happens then?
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
如果崩溃发生在 bwrite 之前，
If the crash happens before bwrite,
是不是我们对内存中 hb 数据结构所做的修改，
isn't the only modification that we've made to the in memory hb data structure,
它不会，它会好的。
so it's not, it's going to be fine.
是的，它是好的，
Yeah, it's gonna be fine,
因为我们已经写入了 db0 dbn 到日志中，
because basically we may have written db1 zero dbn whatever to log,
但是我们还没有成功写入日志头，
but we have not succeeded in writing the log header,
所以，在恢复时，什么都不会发生。
and so will do not, on recovery nothing will happen.
如果正好在 bwrite 后发生崩溃，会发生什么，
And what happens if there's a crash right after to bwrite,
比如这里发生了崩溃。
so like crash here.
它不再是零，
And it's no longer zero,
所以日志头被正确读取并被恢复。
so the log headers correctly read and it's recovered.
是的，会恢复，对吧。
Yeah, will be recovered, correct.
在某一时刻，像我们期望的一样，在恢复期间，
Well, at some point, hopefully during recovery as we expect that,
我们期望恢复会实际读取日志头，
we expect the recovery will actually read the log header
看到其中有一个 5 ，
see that there is a 5 in there for example,
然后把前 5 个日志复制到原位置。
and then copy the first 5 logs to their home location.
所以这一行，
So this is really this, this, this one line,
这个磁盘写入，
there's one disk write,
这个扇区写入是真正的提交点。
there's one sector write is really the commit point.
对吧？
Right?
在提交点之前，事务没有发生，
Before the commitment point, the transaction, is the transaction didn't happen,
在提交点之后，事务一定完成了，
after the commit point, the transaction will definitely be finished,
假设你的恢复是正确的。
assuming your recovery is correct.
好的，让我们回去 commit 。
Okay, so let's you know go back to commit.
所以在提交之后，
So commit, after its committed,
它安装了事务，
it actually installs the transactions,
这非常直接，
and that's pretty straightforward,
它使用数据块，
basically it takes the blocks,
查看数据块所在的头，
looks at the header where the blocks belongs
然后写入那个特定的位置。
and then basically writes into that particular location.
是的，所以我们看看 install_trans ，
Yeah, so we can actually look at install_trans,
看看它是怎么做的。
you see that actually that's what it does.
它有一个日志头的副本，
It has a copy of the log header
并且读取日志头，
and use or reads log header,
它到达目的块的原位置，
it reach the destination block the home location,
将数据从日志块复制到目的位置，
copies the data from the log block into the destination,
然后将缓冲区写入目的位置。
and then writes the buffer to the destination.
好的？
Okay?
所以它所做的是
So basically effectively what this does is
回到上一张幻灯片，
basically you know you go back to this previous slide here
它从日志中复制
and copies, you know it just does these copies from the log
到原位置或文件系统中。
into the home location or actually in the file system.
当然，我们可能会在这个代码中的某个地方出现故障，
And of course you know we might get a failure somewhere in you know this code
或者在我们做这件事的时候，
or while we're doing this,
但是这是可以的，
but you know it should be okay,
因为在恢复中会从头开始。
because hopefully in recovery will start over from the beginning.
让我们看看，这就是安装。
So let's look at we, so that was installed.
所以，一旦安装完成，
So once install is done,
它会将内存中的头重新设置为 0 ，
then basically it sets you know the in-memory header and back to 0
然后写入日志头。
and then writes that log header.
并且引起清理日志，
And effectively that causes to cleans the log,
因为现在是已经是 0 了。
because basically there's now 0 in it.
有什么问题？
Question?
所以，你刚才说的函数，
So, you have the function you're in just before,
比如从什么到什么的东西，
like whereas, does the from to, or to, or something,
它把你要更新的块，
so that puts the, the block that you're going to like update,
你要更新的日志到缓冲区缓存中，
the log that you're going to update into the buffer cache,
是否让它变得更快，
could you make it faster
通过不放入缓冲区缓存，
by not putting into the buffer cache
而是直接写入设备。
and just directly writing it to the device instead.
让我，我们说的是哪个函数？
Let me, which function we're talking about?
我忘了它的名字，
I forget its name,
就是那个复制所有的东西到日志里。
it's the one, where you copy, yeah, everything into the log.
好的， install_trans 。
Okay, install install_trans.
我想是的。
I think so.
哦，也许是这个。
Oh, maybe it was this one.
所以，这个。
So, this.
我想可能是 write_head ，但这是一样的。
I thinking probably of write_head, but it's the same thing.
好的。
Okay, good.
唯一的原因，
The only reason, the only reason to this,
我们的接口不是特别好，
you know basically our interface is not particularly good,
你可以直接读，
you could just read straight,
你可能在想为什么要读，
you know you're wondering why you are doing the read,
没有理由去读，
there's no reason to do the read,
因为我们无论如何都要写，
because we're going to write anyway,
是这个问题吗？
is that the question?
是的，而且你使用了 memmove 。
Yeah, that and you're also doing the memmove.
使用了 memove ，是的，
And did the memmove, yeah,
所以这里是绝对可以优化的代码，
so these are actually a sequence of code can definitely be optimized,
你可以节省一两次磁盘写入。
you can save you know one or two disk writes.
为了简单起见，我们没有做任何这样的事情。
Just for simplicity, we don't do any of that.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thank you.
好的，我想我们已经过了 commit ，
Okay, so I think we're in over commit,
回去，再检查一下。
just like, just go back and double check.
所以我们执行了 write_log ，
So we did the write_log,
我们执行了 write_head ，
we did the write_head
这里是清理操作，
and basically this the cleaning operation,
我们通过给它设置 0 来清除事务。
we erased you know transaction by sending it to zero.
好的？
Okay?
所以，唯一需要进一步了解的是，
So the only thing to further inspect is
恢复是如何进行的，
like how, how does recovery work
所以，恢复发生在 xv6 开始时，
and so recovery happens when you know when xv6 starts,
所以现在我们崩溃了，
so now we had a crash,
系统出了故障，我们重新启动它，
and the system failed, we reboot it,
xv6 首先做的事情之一，
and the, one of the first things that xv6,
xv6 在初始化期间做的一件事，
one of the things that xv6 does during initialization,
它调用 initlog ，
it actually call initlog,
而 initlog 调用 recover_from_log 函数，
and initlog basically calls this function recover_from_log
让我们看看它做了什么。
and so let's see what that does.
recover_from_log 调用 read_head ，
And basically recover_from_log you know calls read_head,
选取或读取。
to basically extract or read the.
让我看看能不能稍微向下滚动一下。
Then, let me see if I can scroll down here a little bit.
从磁盘上读取头，
Basically reads the header from disk,
查看 n ，
and sees if n,
好的，并不是看 n 是否为 0 ，
well, doesn't really see if n is zero or not,
它只是调用 install_trans ，
but it just calls install_trans
这是一样的 install_trans ，
and you know this is exactly the same install_trans
和我们刚才看到的那个。
we use look for it, for a look at it a while ago.
它查看 n ，
And basically you know look at the n
安装从 0 到 n 的所有块
and installs all the blocks from 0 to n
从日志中到它们的原位置。
out of the log into their home location.
如果它完成了，
And if it's done,
一旦它成功了，
once it succeeds,
它也像之前一样清除日志。
you know then actually it calls clear log as before.
所以，这就是恢复所做的，
And so that's actually all what the recovery does,
恢复总是调用安装。
recovery is basically always call does installation.
如果我们在安装时发生故障，
And if we crash during installation here,
也没有什么问题，
no particular problem again, correct,
因为我们崩溃，重启，
because we'll crash, we'll boot,
xv6 重启会调用 loginit ，
xv6 rebooting will call loginit,
它会调用 recover_from_log ，
which will call recover_from_log
并且它会重新安装日志，
and it will basically re-install, replay the log is sometimes called again,
这可能会结束，
and this might have, this might end,
如果我们每次都崩溃或崩溃很多次，
if we crash every time or you know many many times,
我们会多次重新安装日志，
you know we'll re-install or replay the log many many many times,
希望在某一时刻它会成功，
they'll tell hopefully at some point it succeeds
写入所有日志，
and actually you know gets the whole log written,
安装整个日志，
gets the whole log installed,
到原位置。
you know to the, to home locations.
这能理解吗？
Does it make sense?
我有个问题，关于，
I had a question about,
所以，如果一个进程正常运行，
so if a process just runs normally,
它写入一些数据到磁盘中，
it writes some data to disk,
然后在之后的某个时刻，
and then at some point after that,
在提交并安装更改之前，
before it commits and installs the changes,
有一个失败，
there's a failure,
从更多的过程的角度来看，什么都没有发生，
the process, the further process point of view, nothing happened,
但是，
but something like,
我想失败发生在我所做的事情结束后，
I guess the failure happened after the process end of what I was doing,
这有什么不好吗？
so, is there anything bad about that?
不是百分之百明白，
Not hundred percent getting it,
但简短的回答是没什么不好的，
but a short answer is there's nothing bad,
因为磁盘根本不会更新，
because the disk won't be updated at all,
所以就像文件系统操作没有发生一样。
so just as if you know that file system operation didn't happen.
好的，我想。
Alright, I guess.
进程也消失了，
Process disappears too,
但是，无论如何我们不希望进程在故障中幸存下来。
but, you know we don't expect the process to survive failures anyway.
好的，我猜，
Right or I guess,
好的，我想这回答了我的问题，谢谢。
okay I I think that answers my question, thank you.
是的，记住这一点很重要
Yeah, it's important to remember to
在失败中幸存下来的唯一一件事，
basically the only thing that really survives failures
或者具有跨失败的持久性是
or that's persistence across failures is
磁盘或磁盘上的状态，没有别的。
the disk or the state on the disk nothing else, right.
好的，为了让这些更具体化，
Okay, so just to make this all concrete one little more to,
让我们。
let's.
我在 bwrite 放了一个打印语句，
I put a statement in bwrite,
它将内容写入磁盘，
so actually the thing that actually does write to disk,
比如在块缓存中。
like in the block cache.
我们要看看磁盘写入的轨迹是什么。
And we're going to see what the trace of actual disk writes are.
因为在周一，
Because basically on Monday,
我没有说出全部真相，
I sort of, I didn't tell the full truth,
因为我把 print 语句放在 log_write 中，
because basically I put the print statement in log_write
而不是在 bwrite 中，
and not in bwrite,
所以现在我把它放入 bwrite ，
and so now I put it in the bwrite
这样我们就可以看到所有被写入的数据块。
and so we can actually see all the blocks are being written.
我们要做一样的事情，
So we'll do the same thing as before,
也就是 echo hi > x ，
you know echo hi x,
看看真正的磁盘写入。
and just look at actually the actual disk writes.
看看这是否有意义，
And see if that makes sense,
首先要注意的是，
you know so the first thing to note correctly,
这个轨迹比我们上次看到的要长得多，
that this traces way longer than the trace that we looked at last time,
我们在几张幻灯片前看过的那张。
the fact that we looked at a slide a couple slides ago, right.
因为你看到，
Because you're looking at,
刚才演示的，
in fact you know just demonstrate this,
这也是一样的 echo hi 。
here was the same echo hi, correct.
我们看到只有 5 个 log_write 操作，
And when we see there's like only it's 5 log_write operations,
但是它变成了很多磁盘操作。
but it turns into many disk operations, correct.
所以让我们来看看它。
So let's look at it.
所以我们认为 bwrite 3 4 5 是什么，
So what we think bwrite 3 4 and 5 are
以及 bwrite 2 是什么。
and what is bwrite 2.
有人知道吗？
Anybody?
所以先写入日志，然后写入超级块。
So writing to the log and then the super block.
不是超级块。
Not the super block.
抱歉，是 log_head 。
No, sorry, that's the log_head.
是的，看一下，你说对了，
Yeah, so just look at, you got it right,
再看一下这张图片，
you know just looking at this picture again, correct,
日志结构 2 ，
the log structure 2,
这可能是 header 块，
so, that's probably the header block
用来提交记录，
to commit record if you will,
然后 3 是第一个数据块，
and then 3 is the first data block,
4 是第二个数据块，
4 is the second data block,
5 是第三个数据块。
5 is the third data block.
所以回到这里，这是第一次写入，
So going back, you know this is the first write,
第二次写入，第三次写入，
the second write, the third write,
它们都会进入日志，
they're all going into the log
并被写入磁盘，
and they're written to disk,
在磁盘的日志部分中，
in the log log part of the disk,
然后这是提交记录 header 。
and then this is the commit record header.
然后这些是什么？
And then presumably what is this face?
这部分是什么？
What is this part?
这是位图设置吗？
Is that the bitmap setting?
不，那么我们认为 bwrite 3 保存了什么？
No, so what do we think actually stored in this bwrite 3?
这里你创建了文件 x 的 inode ，
Here you creating the file of the inode for x,
更新目录，
updating the directory
然后也创建了文件本身。
and then also actually making the file itself.
是的，所以我们没有在这里做，
Yeah, and so and we didn't do it here, right,
因为在这些 bwrite 中没有发生。
because in these bwrites that didn't happen.
现在我们正在做。
Now we're doing it.
那么，这是事务的哪个阶段？
So what, what what phases of the transaction?
安装更改。
Installing the changes.
是的，安装更改，
Yeah, installing the changes, correct,
我们在这里做的是，
what we did here is,
我们记录写入，
we log the write,
然后，我们提交文件系统操作，
then we committed the file system operation the create operation
现在我们安装它，
and now we're installing it,
现在我们把块放在它们的原位置上。
for now we're putting the blocks in their home location.
现在， bwrite 2 之后是什么？
And now, and what does this bwrite 2 then?
清除日志。
Clearing the log.
是的，清除日志。
Yeah, it's clear log, exactly.
所以，这个这个这个，
So basically this, this, this,
系统调用写入 33 46 32 ，
the system call was writing 33 46 32
使用日志系统，
and to actually do that using the logging system
变成了这组磁盘写入。
that basically turns into this set of disk write, right.
第一部分是安装日志，
Where the first part is installing the log,
第一部分是记录写入，
in the first part is actually logging the writes,
第二部分是安装日志。
in the second part is installing the log.
这是提交记录的两个写入。
And these are the two writes due to commit records.
所以这能理解吗？
So it makes sense?
是否可以从跟踪中找出 begin_op 和 end_op 在哪里？
Is it possible to infer where begin_op and end_op would run from this trace?
嗯，我们不能，
Well, so we're sort of no, correct,
我们不知道 begin_op 是从哪里开始的，
so where did, we don't really know what begin_op start,
但是任何文件系统调用都是以 begin_op 开始的，
but this is any file system calls starts with the begin_op,
并且必须是这种情况，
and it must be the case that,
提交记录在 end_op 中，
the commit record correct is written in end_op,
我们知道这是一些文件系统操作的 end_op 。
so we know that this is the end_op of some file system operation.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，这是 xv6 日志演示，
Okay, so that's basically xv6 log logging in action,
我想讨论一些更复杂的，
and I want talk about a couple complications,
即使是这种很简单日志方案也有其复杂性。
and even this dirt simple naive logging scheme actually has complications.
需要注意的一件事是，
One thing to immediately note of course is,
这是一个很高性能的实现吗？
you know is this a very performance implementation?
你可以看看这个痕迹。
You can by looking at this trace.
不是。
No.
为什么不是，
Why not,
我知道这是两个简单的问题，
I know this is a basically two simple questions,
但提问很重要。
but it's important to ask.
比如，一些东西你写了两次。
Like, you're writing the stuff twice right.
是的，一些东西你写了两次，
Yeah, you're writing the stuff twice,
写一个大文件 f ，
write a file f or a big file f,
我要把那个大文件 f 写两次。
I'm going to write that big file f twice.
所以，这当然不是非常高性能的，
And so, certainly not particularly high performance, right,
我的意思是，将性能削减了一半，
I mean basically re-cutting the performance immediately by a factor of two,
为了崩溃安全。
just to get crash safety.
所以我们会看到，
And so we'll see on on you
在你们阅读周一的 ext3 论文时，
when you're reading the ext ext3 paper for Monday
有一件事你应该记住，
and one thing you should keep in your head,
论文如何，
while reading is get,
如何应对这个倍数 2 。
how, how do I get around for this factor of two.
好的？
Okay?
抱歉，这个情况是不是把 h 和 i 分开写的呢？
Sorry, is it the case that you write the h and the i separately?
是的，我想是的。
Yeah, I think so.
好的。
Okay.
我马上告诉你们为什么，
I'll, I'll show you in a second why,
那里发生了什么。
what is happening there.
或者，
Or maybe,
让我不要做太多回答，
well, let me not commit too much the answer,
但我会回到这个问题上来。
but I will get back to it.
哦，抱歉，是不是有空行，而不是 h 和 i ，但是。
Oh, sorry, am I having the empty line, not the h and i, but yeah.
换行是一个单独的写入，
The new line is a separate write,
h 和 i 是一个写入，换行是一个单独的写入。
h and i is one write, new line is a separate write.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, thank you.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
好的，这些是复杂的问题，
Okay, there's complications
我想稍微谈谈这些复杂的问题。
and I want to talk a little bit about these complications.
这是我们的基本方案，基本数据结构，
Here's our basic scheme, basic data structures,
我想要谈的是三个复杂的问题。
and there's three complications I want to talk about.
也许我可以把它们叫做挑战，不管你怎么称呼。
Maybe I'll call them challenges, whatever you wanna call them.
第一个是驱逐。
The first is eviction.
问题是这样的，
And the issue is as follows,
让我们回到这张图片，
let's say we go back to this picture here,
bcache 已经满了，
and you know bcache is full,
还有正在进行的事务，
and, and sort of transaction in progress,
我们看看，我们刚刚更新了 45 ，
let's see, we've just updated 45,
它现在完成了块 45 ，
it's now done block 45,
所以它要写下一个块，
so it's going to write the next block,
而缓存已经满了。
and the cache is full.
然后，这个，
And, the and,
假设我们没有解决这个问题的办法，
let's say you know we don't we don't have a solution for this yet,
但是缓存决定驱逐 45 ，
but the cache decides, it wants to evict 45 correct,
如果它想驱逐 45 ，
and if it wants to evict 45,
这意味着
but will mean that will mean,
我们必须把它写入原位置。
we have to write it to its home location.
驱逐 45 有什么问题，
How bad would it be to write the block, you know evict 45,
把 45 写入原位置。
and write 45 to home location.
这是好还是坏？
Is that good or bad?
如果我们那样做，会不会违反规则？
Would any rule be broken, if we did that?
我想，如果崩溃发生，
I guess, that as if a crash happens
在同一事务中的其他写操作发生之前，
before the other writes in the same transaction occurs,
那么原子性就被打破了。
then basically atomicity it is broken.
这违反了我所说的这个 write-ahead 规则，
That is basically violates this write-ahead rule that I talked about,
你必须将所有块写入日志，
you have to write all the blocks to the log,
在向每个原位置写入块之前。
before you write any block to each home location.
所以它必须是这种情况，
So it has to be the case correct,
缓存不应该驱逐日志中的任何块。
the cache does not evict any block that sits in the log.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
所以，解决方案是不要驱逐这些在日志中的块。
So the solution is don't evict blocks those are in the log.
这就是刚才展示的内容，
And this is exactly what you were showing a little bit earlier
我说我不想谈。
and said I didn't want to talk about.
所以再次到 log_write ，
So you go to log_write again,
看看这里，
just to see for a second there,
这是 log_write ，
log_write here log_write again
这里我们看到了对 bpin 的调用，
and here we see this call to bpin,
你认为 bpin 会做什么，
and what do you think bpin does,
名字在某种程度上表明了它。
name sort of indicates it.
它把块放入缓存中。
It pins the block in the, in the cache.
是的，它怎么做到的，
Yeah, how does it do it,
因为你已经研究了这个实验。
since you've been looking at this where your current lab extensively.
你觉得它能做什么。
What do you think it does.
我们可以查看 bpin 的实现，
So we can look at the implementation with bpin,
但我们也可以猜猜它是怎么做的。
but we can also guess what it does.
是不是实现它，
Doesn't it essentially just make it,
通过增加 refcnt ，它就不会被驱逐出去。
so that it doesn't get evicted by increasing the ref counts.
是的，这就是它说做的事，
Yeah, exactly this is all thing does,
bpin 只是增加 refcnt ，
bpin just to increases the refcnt
而且我们从 bcache 代码中知道，
and we know from the bcache code, correct,
驱逐不会驱逐任何引用多于 0 的块。
evict won't evict any blocks we have reference higher than 0.
所以，在稍后的日志代码中的某个位置，
And so presumably somewhere later in the logging code,
一旦一件事已经记录，
when once actually a thing is logged,
我们可以解锁块。
we can actually unpin the block, right.
好的，这是一个复杂的问题，
Okay, so that's one complication,
我们有一个固定和解锁的过程。
so we have this pinning and unpinning going on.
我们来看看另一个复杂的问题，
Let's look at another complication,
文件系统操作必须记录在日志中。
you know the file system operations must fit in log.
如果我们回到这里的图片，
If you see, we go back to our picture here,
或者可能这张图片更好，
or actually maybe this is a better picture,
xv6 中的日志有多大？
how big is the log in xv6?
30 个块。
30 blocks.
是的， 30 个块， 32 减去 2 ，
Yeah, 30 blocks, 32 minus 2,
所以最大日志大小是 30 。
so you know max size, max log size is 30.
当然，我们可以提高它，
Of course we could bump it up
在真实的文件系统中运行更大的日志，
in real file system runs with a much bigger log,
但这不重要，
but it doesn't really matter,
无论如何，它是这种情况，
no matter what, it has to be the case, correct,
文件系统操作必须适合 30 个数据块。
the file system operation must fit in 30 blocks.
因为如果文件系统操作尝试写入超过 30 个块，
Because if a file system operation would try to write more to 30 blocks,
那就意味着我们得在这个地方溢出一些东西，
that means we would have to spill something on this location
我们不允许这么做，
and we're not allowed to do that,
因为这会再次违反预写规则。
because that would violate the write-ahead rule again.
所以，必须将每个文件系统操作都写入日志中。
So it has to be the case that every file system operation fits into the log.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
事实上，你知道我们是怎么得到 32 或 30 的？
In fact, you know how do you think we got to 32 or 30?
它与实际适合多少块，有什么关系吗？
Does it have to do anything with how many blocks actually fit?
你需要，
You were a way to
比如最大块数是多少，
like basically how many blocks does the maximum blocks, correct,
文件系统操作可以写入的。
the file system operation could write.
这就是，
And that is really what,
数字 30 必须绝对大于
this number 30 has to be definitely bigger than
文件系统操作可写入的最大数据块数量。
any you know the max number of blocks the file system operation write.
所以，实际上， Robert 和我这样做的，
And so, in fact you know Robert and I did,
因为我们检查了所有文件系统操作，
because we went through all the file system operations,
查看它们，
looked at them
决定最大数量是多少，
and decide whether what's the maximum number is
结果发现数字远远小于 30 ，
and it turns out that the actual number is much lower than the 30,
但我们马上会看到一些有趣的困难的问题，
but you know we'll see in a second a couple interesting complications,
比如，我们目前看到的操作，
like, for example the operation that we look so far,
比如创建文件只有几个块，
like creating a file correct is only a handful of blocks,
这个文件系统操作有 5 个块，
the file system operation is like 5 blocks,
事实上，大多数操作都是为数不多的几个块，
in fact, most operations are a handful of blocks not that many,
你有想到任何可能会写很多很多块的操作吗？
do you think of any operations that might write many many, many blocks?
你在写入一个大文件。
You're write on a huge file.
是的，写入一个很大的文件。
Yeah, write a huge file, right.
所以，如果我们调用 write 系统调用，
So, what if we you know, call the write system call
我们传入一个一兆字节数据的缓存，
and we pass the buffer with have a megabyte of data,
比如一千个块。
like a thousand blocks.
看起来我们遇到了很大的麻烦，
It seems like we're being serious trouble right,
这会违反最大数量。
it would violate you know these maximum.
所以，让我们看看 write ，
And so, let's look at write,
sys_write ，
sys_write,
sys_write 调用 filewrite ，
sys_write calls filewrite,
filewrite ，这里是 filewrite 。
filewrite, here's filewrite.
好的，这里有一个文件描述符 inode ，
Okay, so here's an inode, file descriptor inode
看看我的代码，
and [] see my code
我在显示器上的代码，
or the code that I've on the display
看看这段代码是做什么的。
and notice that what does this code do.
是的，你看上面写的评论，
Yeah, you read the comments write on top here
基本上解释了它，
and then basically explains it,
这是发生了什么，
but this is what happens, correct,
写入被拆分成许多数量较小的写入。
the write is split in many number smaller writes.
所以这里到底发生了什么，
So what really is going on here, correct,
我们确保
we are ensuring that the
整个写入作为一个整体不是原子的，
the whole write is a whole is not atomic,
这没关系， Unix 中的 write 系统调用语义，
that's okay, you know the write Unix system call semantics,
并不需要所有的上千个块，
don't actually require that actually all the thousand blocks,
一兆字节以原子方式写入，
you know a megabyte or actually written atomically
只是要求我们不要损坏文件系统，
and just requires that we don't corrupt the file system,
在写入时，不要损坏文件系统。
between don't corrupt the file system while doing it.
所以我们，
And so basically we,
是的， xv6 将一个大的写入拆分成多个较小的写入，
yeah, xv6 splits a big write in a number of smaller writes
并将它们作为单独的事务写入。
and writes them as individual transactions.
这可以确保我们的示例，
And this would basically ensures that our example,
如果事务分配了一个块编号，
if transaction allocates a block number,
因为我们需要一个新的块作为中间块，
because we need a new block as an intermediate block were,
我们需要一个新的块，
because we need a new block,
因为我们要写入它，
because we're going to write to it,
至少该部分是原子的，
at least that part is completely atomic
并且文件系统永远不会处于不正确的状态，
and the file system will be never left in an incorrect state,
违反任何文件系统不变性。
violating any of the file system invariance.
所以，写入拆分为很多
And so the write is split in many, many,
很多小的写入或很多事务。
many system in many smaller writes or many transactions.
好的？
Okay?
实际上，这是一个主要问题，
In fact, that's the main one that actually is
写入 fs 拆分为多个事务。
write fs split in many, many transactions.
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this?
注意，因为东西放在缓存中，
A note, because you know things are pins correct in cache,
这也意味着块缓存可能大于
that means also that the block cache was may bigger than
大于 logsize 。
the bigger to the logsize.
好的。
Okay.
现在我想谈的最后一个挑战是
So now the final challenge that I want to talk about is
并发文件系统调用。
concurrent file system calls.
这个问题如下，
And the issue as follows,
让我先试着解释一下问题是什么，
let me first try to explain what the problem is
然后我们再看看解决方案是什么。
and then we'll see what the solution is.
假设我们有自己的日志，
So let's say we have our log,
我们正在写如，
and, and we're writing
可能有两个事务同时执行。
and maybe there are two transactions executing concurrently.
想象一下，
And usually imagine for a second,
它们写入很多块，
that you know they write a lot of blocks,
所以 t0 正在执行，
so basically t0 is executing t0 is executing
这里是日志的开头，这里是日志的结尾。
and there also is the beginning of the log, here end of log.
而且， t1 会执行一些块，等等，
And, you know t1 executes some blocks and etc, etc,
而当我们到达日志末尾时，
and by the time we run to the end of the log,
没有一个是完成的，
neither one is complete,
两边都还有更多的写入要做。
you know, so both have still more writes to do.
在这个点上，我们可以提交这两个事务中的任何一个吗？
And, at this point, can we commit any of the two transactions?
不，我们不能，
No, we can't, correct,
因为如果我们提交，事务就是部分完成，
because if we would commit, transaction that is partially done,
那么我们再次违反了预写规则，
then we violate the write-ahead rule again
而且日志的目的是行不通的。
and you know the purpose actually logging there doesn't work out.
因此情况必须是，
So it has to be the case,
多个并发事务可以放入日志中，
that basically a number of concurrent transactions must fit in the log,
其实所有的并发操作，都必须符合。
in fact all concurrent operations, must fit.
所以，在这种情况下，
And so, in the way,
所以这是一种挑战，
so this is sort of a challenge, correct,
我们有一个文件系统调用开始，
we have a file system call starting
我们必须安排，
and you know we gotta arranged basically the that we,
我们有一个入口做检查，
we basically do a sort of an entrance you know check,
在我们运行文件系统操作之前，
you know before we actually let the file system operation go,
我们必须检查是否还有足够的块，
we must check whether there actually is enough blocks still,
如果我们已经有 n 个文件系统操作正在进行，
you know if we have n file system operations already in progress,
我们必须确保，如果我们允许多一个开始，
we have to make sure that if we allow one more guy to start,
块的总数，
that actually the total number of blocks, right,
它们可以一起写入，放入日志中。
they could write together actually fits in the log.
xv6 解决这个问题，
And the way you know basically xv6 you know gets around this,
限制并发文件系统调用的数量。
basically limits the number of concurrent file system calls.
它的工作方式是，
And the way it basically works is that,
我们看到 begin_op ，
and begin_op you would see,
有多少未完成的并发文件正在处理中，
how many outstanding concurrent files with transaction are in progress,
如果正在进行的太多，
if there are too many in progress,
我们只是存储当前的文件系统操作，然后进入睡眠状态，
we just stock the current file system operation and goes to sleep
它将等到所有其他文件操作完成并提交。
and it will wait until all the other guys are done and have committed.
所有其他文件操作都会一起提交，
And all the other guys will commit together,
事实上， t1 t2 ，它们已经完成了，
in fact you know at some point t1 t2, they're basically done,
可能 t3 也在这里，
maybe t3 in there too,
它们完成了，
they finish
然后所有这些事务，
and then basically in all these transactions
同一时间一起提交，
and in single time a single basically committed together,
这有时称为组提交。
this is sometimes called group commit.
因为你提交多个系统调用，
Because you're committing multiple system calls,
所有并发运行的系统调用，
you know all the ones that were concurrent in action,
作为一个大事务提交，
you committed together as a single big transactions,
所以所有更新都是可见的。
so that all there updates are visible.
所以，所有更新，全部，
So that all there updates, all place, all,
所以，所有这些更新，
so that all there updates,
全部发生或一个都没有发生。
all take place or none of them take place.
好的？
Okay?
我们可以看到，如果你去。
And we can see that you know, if you go to.
一个简短的问题。
A quick question.
嗯。
Yeah.
这个组提交是否是必须的，
Is that, is the group commit, is the group commit necessary,
比如一个系统调用首先完成，
could you say if one system calls finish first,
先提交它的事务，
just commit it's it's transaction
然后在提交其他的，
and then commit other ones later,
或者它是必要的。
or is it a necessary property.
你必须非常小心，
You gotta be very careful,
因为你还记得，
because you remember,
我一开始并没有明确地把它说成是一个目标，
one thing I didn't really state it explicitly as a goal early on
是因为我们仍按写入顺序执行系统调用，
is that we basically execute the system calls still in the write order,
right,
如果一个写入，
if a if a if a write,
如果读取观察到写入，
if a read observes write
然后做一个写入，
and then does a write,
那么必须是，
then it has to be the case,
第二次写入发生在第一次写入之后。
that that second write happens later than the first write.
这是一个日志，
And the reason that this is a log, correct,
因为这反映了还没有发生的写入的顺序。
because that basically reflects the order in which the writes haven't happened.
所以，你可以修改日志中的写入顺序，
And so you can really really nearly changed the order of the writes in the log,
因为这会产生了怪异的行为。
because that maybe actually result into bizarre behavior,
从用户程序的角度来看。
observable by user programs.
所以必须是这样的，
And so that has to be the case
你按操作发生的顺序进行提交，
that basically you commit you know the operations of these actions in the order they happened,
我们也按照发生的顺序执行写入。
we also perform the writes in the order they happened.
所以一般来说，它更安全，
And so in general you know, it's, it's safer,
把它们放在一起提交是安全的，
you know it's safe to basically commit them all together
总是保持良好的[]。
you're always in good [].
好的？
Okay?
好问题。
Good question, though.
好的，我想回来，看另一件事，
Okay I just want to go back to one more thing,
看看 begin_op ，虽然我说了一点，
and then look at the begin_op, yet I talked a little bit,
因为，之前我说现在不想谈论这个。
because like I don't want to talk about it right now.
但是，这里我们可以看到。
But, there we can see.
这里是 begin_op ，
So here's the begin_op,
首先，如果准备好提交日志，
first of all, if we're ready committing the log,
我们就等日志提交，
we're just gonna wait until the log has committed,
因为我们现在不能写入日志，
because you know we can't write to the log
在日志安装时。
while the log actually being installed.
如果我们结束了，
If we're end,
并发操作超过 logsize ，
concurrent operation that basically makes us go across the logsize,
我们可以进入睡眠状态，
we could go to sleep,
等待所有前面的并发事务完成，
and wait until basically all the preceding concurrent transactions are done,
如果我们被允许继续执行，
and if we're allowed to proceed
就是入口是允许的，
basically are entrance is allowed,
我们对 log.outstanding 加一，
we increase log.outstanding by 1,
因为它们反映了我们的情况，
because they reflect our thing
然后我们继续，
and then we basically proceed
并开始执行文件系统操作。
and start doing file system operations.
如果你再看一下 end_op ，为了。
And if you look at end_op again, just to.
所以，你可以看到 end_op 将 log.outstanding 减一，
So you see the end_op basically decreases log.outstanding by one,
因为一个事务完成了。
because one transaction is finished.
当然处于提交状态是错误的，引起 panic ，
It certainly would be an error in committing states, with panic in that case
如果我们是这组并发事务中的最后一个，
and we actually are the last one from that set of concurrent transactions,
而且 log.outstanding 是 0 ，
then, actually, and log.outstanding goes to 0,
我们就开始提交。
we immediately start committing.
然后当我们完成的时候，
And then when we're done,
我们，我们不是日志，
we're when actually, if we're not the log,
是的，我们提交。
yeah, yeah, we commit.
如果还有剩余空间，
And if there's space you know left,
我们会叫醒那个日志，
we wake up the guy,
这样就可以开始执行了。
so they can actually start running.
好的？
Okay?
所以即使这个极其简单的文件系统，
So even though this dirt simple file system,
xv6 的非常简单的日志系统，
that are just dirt simple logging system that xv6
也有一堆复杂的东西。
actually has a bunch of complications.
我的时间快到了，
So I'm starting to run out of time,
我就在这里结束吧。
so let me wrap up here.
所以总而言之，
So in summary,
我们谈论的是日志，
you know what we what we talk about is basically logging,
作为崩溃安全的解决方案，
as a solution for, for crash safety,
或者是多步文件系统操作的解决方案。
or really for multi-step file system operations.
到目前为止，
And you know if you've seen so far,
它对崩溃安全非常有效，
it works great for crash safety,
但是性能，这将是周一的主题，
but you know performance, and that's going to be the topic for Monday
当你阅读周一的 ext3 文件系统论文时，
and as you read the ext3 file system paper for Monday,
这是你应该考虑的事情。
you know that's the thing you should be thinking about.
好的，还有关于文件系统的问题吗？
Okay, any more file system questions?
任何要离开的人，请随意离开，
In fact anybody who has to leave, please feel free to leave,
但如果你还想再多问几个问题，那就继续。
but if you want to hang around and ask more questions, you know, please do so.
哦，我有一个关于缓存大小和日志大小的问题，
Oh, I have a question regarding cache size and the log size,
所以你说缓存大小必须大于日志大小，
so you said that the cache size has to be great as big as the log size,
但在这个示例中，它们的大小似乎是一样的，
but they seem to be the same size for this case,
所以这是否意味着如果日志放入 30 个缓存，
so is that means that if the log pins 30 buffers
然后一些其他操作试图做一些事情，
and then some other operation tries to do something,
它只是失败了，
it just fails,
因为缓存中的插槽没有空闲的。
because it it runs out of a free slots in the buffer.
不，也许我们来看看，
No, maybe let's let's look at the,
好的，那么，
okay, so,
让我先检查一件事。
let me first check one thing.
好的，我们看看 bio 。
Okay, let's go to bio.
好的。
Yeah, okay.
让我们首先检查 NBUF 是否大于 LOGSIZE ，
Let's actually first check NBUF is bigger than size of LOGSIZE, the buffer cache,
好的，它设置为某个大小。
okay, so it's set up to something big.
所以，如果我们找不到，会发生什么，
So what happens actually if we can't find,
bget 找不到缓存，
bget can't find a buffer,
实际会引起 panic 。
actually it's panics.
所以，我们，
And, so we we,
缓存里没有空闲的位置，
there's no free slot in the buffer cache,
xv6 引起 panic ，
you know xv6 panic,
这不是很理想，
that's not particularly ideal,
事实上会很糟糕，
in fact would be terrible
所以你希望永远不会出现这种情况，
and so you hope never to be in this situation
希望挑选正确的数字，不太可能发生。
and hopefully picked numbers correctly basically is unlikely to happen.
但是，为什么我们不能返回一个错误。
But why can't we return an error.
因为这似乎是最明显的做法，
Because that seems like the obvious thing to do, like,
如给给调用方返回一个错误，
if return an error to the caller
而调用方可能返回给文件系统接口，
and the caller maybe returns back up to the file system interface
只需要返回 -1 ，表示这个操作失败了。
and just return -1 saying like oh this operation failed.
为什么这是个问题？
Why is that a problem?
所以考虑这个是，
So ready to think about this is
许多文件系统操作都是多步操作，
that you know many file system operations are multi-step operations, right,
正如我们看到的，
as we've seen now,
在这节课和上一节课中，
in this lecture and in the previous lecture
比如，我们写了两次，然后写第三次，
and let's say, we did two writes and then the third write,
我们遇到了这样的情况，
we run into this case,
我们不能进行写入，
where we can't actually do the write,
因为块缓存里已经没有地方了，
because there's no place in the block cache,
我们已经写了两次了。
we have done two writes, right.
我们能不能跳出文件系统调用。
Can we just bail out of the file system call.
好的，我明白了。
Okay, I see right.
我们不能，
We cannot, correct,
因为我们可能已经更新某个文件的目录块，
because we might have updated to in the directory, directory block of some file,
如果我们需要更新某个目录中的目录块，
if we might have to update the directory block in some directory,
如果我们想让它工作，
and if we wanted to make this work,
我们需要做的就是撤销这些更改，
what we would have to do is undo those changes,
就像我们以前所做的任何写入一样，
like any writes that we did before,
作为系统调用的一部分，我们必须撤消。
as part of that system call, we have to undo.
好的。
Okay.
那很痛苦，这就是我们不做的原因。
That was painful, that's what we don't do it.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense?
好的，所以这不是问题，
Okay so it's not a problem,
如果日志记录所有东西，
if the log the log pins everything
缓存中没有更多空间，
and there's no more space for cache,
但它只会引起 panic ，好的。
but it will just panic, okay.
是的，当然这种 panci 从来没有真正发生过，
Yeah, of course this panic never really happen,
只有极少数的情况可能会发生。
like there's a only corner cases where this hopefully happens.
我想你只是，
I guess you just,
好的，有道理，
okay, yeah, that makes sense,
好的，谢谢。
okay, thank you.
还有什么问题吗？
Any more questions?
我有个问题是关于，
I have a question about,
我想是关于我之前的组提交，
I guess following up my earlier one about the group commits,
我试着去想，
I was trying to think of,
我想我从高层级上理解了，
like I think I kind of understand it a high level,
我想确认一下，
I was trying to make sure,
我理解具体的例子，为什么它很重要，
I understand concrete example, why it is important
可能这是一个例子，展示了它，
and may is this an example that kind of demonstrates its,
我猜我在想这样一种情况，
like I guess I was thinking of a situation
你有，这可能是错综复杂的，
where you have say like this might be convoluted,
比如一个进程生成 1 到 n 的数字流，
like one process generating a stream of numbers like one to n
然后两个进程消耗，
and then two processes consuming,
可能它们在接收同一个管道，
that maybe they're listening on the same pipe,
比如 n 在一个偶数停止，
and say like n like stops an even number,
一个进程消耗并打印出奇数，
one process is consuming and printing out the odd numbers,
一个进程是消耗偶数部分，
one process is consuming part of the even numbers,
如果没有组提交，
and if you didn't have group commits,
那么正确的行为，
so like the correct behavior
比如它们打印写入同一个文件，
and say they're printing it for like their writing the same file,
所以正确的行为应该是
and so the correct behavior would be
在这一切结束的时候，
at the end of at the end of all this,
你可能希望文件含有偶数，
you would expect the file to have like an even number,
即最后一个数字，
like the last number,
但是如果你没有组提交，
but if you didn't have group commits,
可能倒数第二个进程在最后一个进程之后提交，
it's possible that the second to last process actually gets committed after the last one
并且它看到的是 9 ，
and it actually see nine,
这是不是一个正确的例子，为什么这很重要。
is just like a correct example, why this is important.
我想我得仔细考虑一下，
I think I have to think a little bit more carefully about it,
但这绝对是问题的症结所在，
but that is definitely the flavour of the problem,
如果重新排序系统调用，可能会遇到。
you might run into if you reorder system calls.
好的，好的。
Okay, okay.
我在讲稿中有一个很好的例子，
I have a great example in the lecture note,
讲稿中的，
if the lecture notes,
shell 命令的行为会变得奇怪，
you know shell command that really you know behave weirdly
if you didn't commit to,
这并不是组提交的问题，
this is not really an issue in some sense from group commit,
但确实是一个事务需要按顺序提交的问题。
is really an issue that transactions need to be committed in order.
嗯，我明白了，
Mhm, I see,
如果没有组提交，那么。
and group if it didn't have group commit, then.
是的，人们可能会想
Yeah, people might think
如果没有组提交，
like well what if you don't have group commit,
然后就会有一种情况，
then there's a temptation
就是提交一些后面的事务，
to basically you know commit some later transaction,
因为它已经完成了，
because it's already finished,
但是第一个还没有完成，
but the first one isn't finished yet,
为了创造空间，
and to create space,
但这不是解决方法。
but that's not a solution.
好的，理解了，
Okay, that makes sense,
在课堂上的什么地方有这个例子？
where in the lecture notes this example of?
我想是 shell 命令，
I think shell command,
说明了顺序是重要的。
where were illustrated by ordering is important.
好的。
Okay.
它不是直接与组提交关联的，
It doesn't, it doesn't tie it directly to a group commits,
但它说明了对系统调用进行排序很重要。
but it basically makes the point that ordering system calls is important.
我明白了，这是不是像文本那样。
I see, is this in the the like the text.